<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vra xmlns="http://www.vraweb.org/vracore4.htm" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.vraweb.org/vracore4.htm http://cluster-schemas.uni-hd.de/vra-strictCluster.xsd">
    <work id="w_Ex016_paintings_CubistPainting" refid="c_CCO_Examples">
        <agentSet>
	    <display>Pablo Picasso (Spanish, 1881-1973)</display>
            <agent dataDate="2015-05-04-09-37-13">
                <dates type="life">
                    <earliestDate circa="false">1881</earliestDate>
                    <latestDate circa="false">1973</latestDate>
                </dates>
                <name refid="15873" type="personal" vocab="viaf">Picasso, Pablo</name>
                <role type="code" vocab="marcrelator">art</role>
            </agent>
        </agentSet>
        <culturalContextSet>
            <culturalContext vocab="AAT" refid="300111188">French (culture or style)</culturalContext>
        </culturalContextSet>
        <dateSet>
            <date type="creation" dataDate="2015-05-04-09-40-11" source="Museum of Modern Art">
                <earliestDate>
                    <date circa="false">1907-06</date>
                </earliestDate>
		<latestDate>
                    <date circa="false">1907-07</date>
		</latestDate>
            </date>
        </dateSet>
        <descriptionSet>
            <description pref="true" source="Museum of Modern Art online. www.moma.org (accessed 29 July 2006)">
                <text>In this epoch-making work, which prefigured Cubism, Picasso amalgamated the simplified iconic forms with Cézanne’s reduction of the underlying structure of natural forms. The artist modeled several faces on African masks and iconic Iberian forms.</text>
                <author>
                    <name refid="131347215" type="corporate" vocab="viaf">Visual Resources Association</name>
                    <role type="code" vocab="marcrelator">edt</role>
                </author>
            </description>	
            <description pref="false" source="Museum of Modern Art" dataDate="2015-05-04-09-41-43">
                <text>Les Demoiselles d’Avignon marks a radical break from traditional composition and perspective in painting. It depicts five naked women with figures composed of flat, splintered planes and faces inspired by Iberian sculpture and African masks. The compressed space the figures inhabit appears to project forward in jagged shards; a fiercely pointed slice of melon in the still life of fruit at the bottom of the composition teeters on an impossibly upturned tabletop. These strategies would be significant in Picasso’s subsequent development of Cubism, charted in this gallery with a selection of the increasingly fragmented compositions he created in this period.

Picasso unveiled the monumental painting in his Paris studio after months of revision. The Avignon of the work’s title is a reference to a street in Barcelona famed for its brothel. In Picasso’s preparatory studies for the work, the figure at the left was a man, but the artist eliminated this anecdotal detail in the final painting.</text>
                <author>
                    <name refid="163771056" type="corporate" vocab="viaf">Museum of Modern Art, NY</name>
                    <role type="code" vocab="marcrelator">rps</role>
                </author>
            </description>
            <description pref="false" source="The Museum of Modern Art, MoMA Highlights, New York: The Museum of Modern Art, revised 2004, originally published 1999, p. 64">
                <text>Les Demoiselles d'Avignon is one of the most important works in the genesis of modern art. The painting depicts five naked prostitutes in a brothel; two of them push aside curtains around the space where the other women strike seductive and erotic poses—but their figures are composed of flat, splintered planes rather than rounded volumes, their eyes are lopsided or staring or asymmetrical, and the two women at the right have threatening masks for heads. The space, too, which should recede, comes forward in jagged shards, like broken glass. In the still life at the bottom, a piece of melon slices the air like a scythe.

The faces of the figures at the right are influenced by African masks, which Picasso assumed had functioned as magical protectors against dangerous spirits: this work, he said later, was his "first exorcism painting." A specific danger he had in mind was life-threatening sexual disease, a source of considerable anxiety in Paris at the time; earlier sketches for the painting more clearly link sexual pleasure to mortality. In its brutal treatment of the body and its clashes of color and style (other sources for this work include ancient Iberian statuary and the work of Paul Cézanne), Les Demoiselles d'Avignon marks a radical break from traditional composition and perspective.</text>
                <author>
                    <name refid="163771056" type="corporate" vocab="viaf">Museum of Modern Art, NY</name>
                    <role type="code" vocab="marcrelator">rps</role>
                </author>
            </description>
            <description pref="false" source="MoMA Learning" href="https://www.moma.org/learn/moma_learning/pablo-picasso-les-demoiselles-davignon-paris-june-july-1907">
                <text>Of Primal Instincts and Formal Innovations: Picasso’s Les Demoiselles d’Avignon

Among Picasso’s profuse output of more than 20,000 paintings, prints, drawings, sculptures, ceramics, theater sets, and costume designs is Les Demoiselles d’Avignon (1907). In this painting, he did away with pre-existing artistic conventions, like naturalism and perspective, hurling even the most forward-thinking viewers into a future they weren’t quite ready for.

Picasso was a 25-year-old Spanish immigrant to France when he painted Les Demoiselles d’Avignon, working in a cramped warren of studios on the Parisian hill of Montmartre. The story of its making begins with hundreds of preparatory paintings and drawings, which he generated over an intensive six-month period, working out his ideas. They reflected Picasso’s responses to Paul Cézanne’s structured, almost sculptural depiction of objects and figures and his prismatic structuring of space in his still lifes and scenes of bathers. They also reflected his fascination with the African, Iberian, and Oceanic masks and statuary populating France’s ethnographic museums, as well as the lusts and anxieties wrapped up in his own, complex relationships with women.

Out of this intellectual-emotional tumult came a painting in which form and content were equalized. Its title, which translates to “The Young Women of Avignon,” refers to Avignon Street in Barcelona, home to the prostitutes the artist frequented. The five women’s pinkish-peach-colored bodies, appearing larger than human-scale, fill the space of the painting, which is eight feet high by just over seven feet wide. The women’s shoulders, hips, and limbs are depicted with angular lines and flat, geometric planes. Cubic shapes or, in the case of the woman standing left of center, half-circles, form their breasts. Their faces, too, are sharp-edged and radically simplified, especially those of the two women at right, which he modeled directly after African masks.

As his preparatory studies reveal, Picasso initially conceived of the figure at the left of the painting as a male medical student, in the act of entering the brothel. Deciding that such a narrative detail would interfere with the work’s visual impact, he ultimately transformed the figure into a fifth prostitute. The women emerge from brown, white, and blue curtains that look like shattered glass, their bodies thrust forward toward the viewer by the scene’s lack of depth. Their eyes—enormous and almond-shaped, and inspired by African and Iberian carvings—are fixed daringly on the viewer. Near their feet sits a small arrangement of fruit, with a scythe-like sliver of melon set behind a bunch of grapes, an apple, and a pear, and which, like the women’s bodies, seems too sharp to touch.</text>
                <author>
                    <name refid="163771056" type="corporate" vocab="viaf">Museum of Modern Art, NY</name>
                    <role type="code" vocab="marcrelator">rps</role>
                </author>
            </description>
            <description pref="false" source="Museum of Modern Art">
                <text>Provenance.
The artist, Paris. 1907 - 1924
Jacques Doucet (1853-1929), Neuilly (Paris). Purchased from Picasso in February 1924 - 1929
Madame Jacques Doucet (Jeanne Roger), Neuilly. 1929 - September 1937
Jacques Seligmann &amp; Co., New York. Purchased from Madame Doucet in September 1937
The Museum of Modern Art, New York. Purchased from Seligmann, through the Lillie P. Bliss Bequest, in 1937. Transaction completed in 1939</text>
                <author>
                    <name refid="163771056" type="corporate" vocab="viaf">Museum of Modern Art, NY</name>
                    <role type="code" vocab="marcrelator">rps</role>
                </author>
            </description>
        </descriptionSet>
        <locationSet>
            <location pref="true" type="repository" dataDate="2015-05-04-09-44-54">
		        <refid type="accession">333.1939</refid> 
                <name refid="163771056" vocab="viaf" type="corporate">Museum of Modern Art, New York</name>
          		<name refid="7007567" vocab="tgn" type="geographic" extent="inhabited place">New York</name>
          		<name refid="7007568" vocab="tgn" type="geographic" extent="state">New York</name>
          		<name refid="7012149" vocab="tgn" type="geographic" extent="nation">United States</name>
          		<name refid="1000001" vocab="tgn" type="geographic" extent="continent">North and Central America</name>
            </location>
            <location pref="false" type="creation" source="Museum of Modern Art, NY">
		        <refid type="other">Picasso unveiled the monumental painting in his Paris studio after months of revision.</refid>
                <name refid="7008038" vocab="tgn" type="geographic" extent="inhabited place">Paris</name>
          		<name refid="1000070" vocab="tgn" type="geographic" extent="nation">France</name>
          		<name refid="1000003" vocab="tgn" type="geographic" extent="continent">Europe</name>
            </location>
        </locationSet>
        <materialSet>
            <material refid="300015050" type="medium" vocab="aat">oil paint</material>
            <material refid="300014078" type="support" vocab="aat">canvas</material>
        </materialSet>
        <measurementsSet>
            <measurements source="Museum of Modern Art, NY" pref="true" type="height" unit="cm">243.9</measurements>
            <measurements source="Museum of Modern Art, NY" pref="true" type="width" unit="cm">233.7</measurements>
            <measurements source="Museum of Modern Art, NY" pref="false" type="height" unit="ft">8'</measurements>
            <measurements source="Museum of Modern Art, NY" pref="false" type="width" unit="ft">7' 8"</measurements>
        </measurementsSet>
        <relationSet>
            <relation type="imageIs" relids="i_Ex016_paintings_CubistPainting">general view</relation>
        </relationSet>
       	<rightsSet>
       	    <display>© 2018 Estate of Pablo Picasso / Artists Rights Society (ARS), New York; Acquired through the Lillie P. Bliss Bequest (by exchange)  </display>
       	    <rights type="copyrighted">
          		<rightsHolder>Estate of Pablo Picasso</rightsHolder>
          		<rightsHolder>Artists Rights Society (ARS)</rightsHolder>
          		<text>© 2018 Estate of Pablo Picasso / Artists Rights Society (ARS), New York </text>
       	    </rights>
       	    <rights type="other">
          		<rightsHolder>Museum of Modern Art, NY</rightsHolder>
          		<text>Acquired through the Lillie P. Bliss Bequest (by exchange)</text>
       	    </rights>
       	</rightsSet>
        <sourceSet>
            <source pref="false">
                <refid type="URI">http://www.moma.org/collection/object.php?object_id=79766</refid>
                <name type="electronic">Museum of Modern Art, NY</name>
            </source>
            <source pref="true" dataDate="2015-05-04-09-58-49">
                <refid type="URI">http://cco.vrafoundation.org/index.php/toolkit/index_of_examples/category_examples_4_paintings/example_16_cubist_painting</refid>
                <name type="electronic">Cataloging Cultural Objects Commons. Example 16: Cubist painting.</name>
            </source>
            <source pref="false">
                <refid type="URI">http://vocab.getty.edu/page/cona/700000104</refid>
                <name type="electronic">CONA</name>
            </source>
        </sourceSet>
        <stylePeriodSet>
            <stylePeriod refid="300021495" vocab="aat">Cubist</stylePeriod>
            <stylePeriod source="Museum of Modern Art, NY" refid="300174254" vocab="aat">Primitivist</stylePeriod>
        </stylePeriodSet>
        <subjectSet>
            <subject dataDate="2015-05-04-09-49-37">
                <term refid="300189808" vocab="aat" type="descriptiveTopic">figures</term>
            </subject>
            <subject>
                <term refid="300025943" vocab="aat" type="descriptiveTopic">women</term>
            </subject>
            <subject dataDate="2015-05-04-09-48-40">
                <term refid="300189568" vocab="aat" type="descriptiveTopic">nudes</term>
            </subject>
            <subject>
                <term refid="300007218" vocab="aat" type="otherTopic">brothels</term>
            </subject>
            <subject>
                <term refid="300189323" vocab="aat" type="conceptTopic">prostitution</term>
            </subject>
            <subject>
                <term refid="300011868" vocab="aat" type="descriptiveTopic">fruit</term>
            </subject>
            <subject>
                <term refid="300343731" vocab="aat" type="iconographicTopic">tribal art</term>
            </subject>
            <subject>
                <term refid="300138758" vocab="aat" type="descriptiveTopic">masks</term>
            </subject>
            <subject>
                <term refid="300305500" vocab="aat" type="geographicPlace">Iberian</term>
            </subject>
	    <subject>
		<term refid="7008799" vocab="tgn" type="geographicPlace">Avignon</term>
	    </subject>
        </subjectSet>
        <techniqueSet>
            <technique refid="300054216" vocab="aat">painting</technique>
            <technique refid="300178684" vocab="aat">oil painting</technique>
        </techniqueSet>
        <titleSet>
            <title pref="true" type="repository">Les Demoiselles d’Avignon</title>
            <title pref="false" type="translated" source="HRA">The Women of Avignon</title>
            <title pref="false" type="descriptive">Five Female Nudes</title>
        </titleSet>
        <worktypeSet>
            <worktype refid="300033618" vocab="aat">paintings</worktype>
            <worktype refid="300033799" vocab="aat">oil paintings</worktype>
        </worktypeSet>
    </work>
   <image id="i_Ex016_paintings_CubistPainting"
          href="http://www.moma.org//media/W1siZiIsIjE1MTI3MSJdLFsicCIsImNvbnZlcnQiLCItcmVzaXplIDIwMDB4MjAwMFx1MDAzZSJdXQ.jpg?sha=f7560007ccdf470f">
      <agentSet>
          <agent>
            <name refid="163771056" type="corporate" vocab="viaf">Museum of Modern Art</name>
            <role type="code" vocab="marcrelator">cre</role>
         </agent>
      </agentSet>
      <relationSet>
         <relation type="imageOf"
                   relids="w_Ex016_paintings_CubistPainting">attachment</relation>
      </relationSet>
      <rightsSet>
         <rights type="copyrighted">
            <rightsHolder>Museum of Modern Art, NY</rightsHolder>
            <text>Digital image, The Museum of Modern Art, New York/Scala, Florence.</text>
         </rights>
      </rightsSet>
      <sourceSet>
         <source dataDate="2015-05-04-09-34-17">
            <refid type="URI">https://www.moma.org/collection/works/79766</refid>
            <name type="electronic">Museum of Modern Art, NY</name>
         </source>
      </sourceSet>
      <titleSet>
         <title type="generalView">Les Demoiselles d'Avignon </title>
      </titleSet>
   </image>
</vra>
