<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vra xmlns="http://www.vraweb.org/vracore4.htm" xmlns:ext="http://exist-db.org/vra/extension" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:hra="http://cluster-schemas.uni-hd.de" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.vraweb.org/vracore4.htm http://cluster-schemas.uni-hd.de/vra-strictCluster.xsd">
    <work id="w_daf117f2-d7dd-47fb-b318-61b4fbf3c1e5" source="Kurs" refid="c_70311af2-d3de-4606-9d17-64b373800ce2">
        <agentSet>
    <display/>
    <notes/>
    <agent dataDate="2015-04-22-14-22-17" pref="false">
        <attribution/>
        <culture/>
        <dates type="life">
            <earliestDate circa="false" type="">1826</earliestDate>
            <latestDate circa="false" type=""/>
        </dates>
        <name refid="96560529" source="viaf" type="personal" vocab="viaf">Hodgson, Isaac</name>
        <role type="code" vocab="marcrelator">arc</role>
    </agent>
</agentSet>
        <dateSet>
    <display> ground broken in 1871, completed in 1874</display>
    <notes/>
    <date dataDate="2016-03-24-09-15-30" pref="false" type="creation">
        <earliestDate>
            <date circa="false" type="">1871</date>
        </earliestDate>
        <latestDate>
            <date circa="false" type="">1874</date>
        </latestDate>
    </date>
</dateSet>
        <descriptionSet>
    <display/>
    <notes/>
    <description dataDate="2015-04-22-14-37-37" href="http://pdfhost.focus.nps.gov/docs/NRHP/Text/79000031.pdf" pref="false" type="">
        <text>The Bartholomew County Courthouse is the only surviving example of the French Second Empire style in the county. It was designed "by noted Indiana architect Isaac Kodgson of Indianapolis and completed in 1874.
The building is an ell-shaped mall, with the intersection of its legs at the northeast corner of Washington and Third Street. The extreme ends of the wings extend behind to the south and west; the apis thus formed on the south-west contains a grandstaircase. The bays at the ends of the wings are projected to form corner pavilions, as are those at the intersection of the  wings, which form the base of the clocktower. All elements are crowned by steeply inclined mansard roofs; those of the corner pavilions and tower additionally have roof curbs exaggerated into modillionated cornices with panelled friezework and elaborate roof cresting.
The red pressed brick walls are trimmed in white limestone and stand on a plinth and watertable of smooth rusticated blue limestone. This polychrome effect is 'used to emphasize openings .and horizontals, since the lines of the sills, spandrels, sash,
and arch imposts are continued as ashlar coursing set flush with the face brick and continuous over openings. The same device is used to emphasize vertical lines on the corner pavilions and the slightly projecting central bay of the east elevation, each of which have smooth rusticated quoins and central window bays enframed by pilasters and variously capped with pediments or round arches with panelled spandrels. On the main (east) elevation, the entrance is within an arcade of segmental arches let into the recess formed by the corner pavilions; the arches and the Corinthian columns from which they directly spring, as well as the open balustrade above, are all constructed of limestone. The slightly projecting central bay behind this arcade extends above the principal cornice line and is capped with a broken pediment flanked by finials. The central window of the bay is enframed by pilasters and volute buttresses and surmounted by a commemorative inscription whose segmental cap-mould breaks the pediment.
On the north elevation, a centrally placed entrance is beneath a distyle Corinthian portico whose design echoes the arcade on the east facade. Directly above the portico is a round-arched window bay whose panelled surround marches 'that of the
central bay of the east facade.
The clocktower is the other principal feature'of'tlie exterior; it extends three stories above the cornice line. The elevations of the fourth and fifth floor levels are composed of a central elongated window bay, with a panelled apron, narrow sidelights separated from the bay by the enframing pilasters, and a round arch at the top with panelled spandrel and flanking oculi. On the sixth level each facade has five arcaded, louvred openings for the belfry, and is surmounted by a broad Corinthian entablature. Above this there is a broad curb at the base of the vertically elongated mansard. The clockfaces above are iron framings with white glass infill; they are mounted directly onto the roofing, without decorative surrounds.
The appearance of the roofline has been altered substantially. In 1953 the original slate roof was replaced with the present standing-seam copper; at that time dormers and cresting were also removed. The wrought iron cresting has since been
reproduced with an alloy facsimile.</text>
        <author>
            <name refid="122853047" source="viaf" type="corporate" vocab="viaf">National Register of Historic Places</name>
            <role type="code" vocab="marcrelator">aut</role>
        </author>
    </description>
</descriptionSet>
        <locationSet>
    <display/>
    <notes/>
    <location dataDate="2016-03-24-09-17-45" pref="false" type="site">
                                <refid type=""/>
                                <name refid="7013644" type="geographic" vocab="tgn">Columbus</name>
                                <point epsg="">
                                    <lat/>
                                    <long/>
                                </point>
                            </location>
            <location dataDate="2015-04-22-14-39-51" pref="false" type="site">
        <refid type=""/>
        <name type="geographic">234 Washington St, Columbus, IN 47201, USA</name>
        <point epsg="4326">
            <lat>39.201071</lat>
            <long>-85.921403</long>
        </point>
    </location>
</locationSet>
        <materialSet>
    <display/>
    <notes/>
    <material pref="false" refid="300010540" source="getty" type="medium" vocab="aat">face brick</material>
            <material pref="false" refid="300011286" source="getty" type="medium" vocab="aat">limestone</material>
</materialSet>
        <measurementsSet>
    <display/>
    <notes/>
    <measurements pref="false" shape="" type="count" unit="stories">2</measurements>
</measurementsSet>
        <sourceSet>
    <display/>
    <notes/>
    <source dataDate="2015-04-22-14-38-06" pref="false">
                                <refid type="URI">http://pdfhost.focus.nps.gov/docs/NRHP/Text/79000031.pdf</refid>
                                <name type="electronic">National Register of Historic Places</name>
                            </source>
            <source dataDate="2015-04-22-14-21-18" pref="false">
        <refid type="URI">http://cco.vrafoundation.org/downloads/PartTwo_5-LocationGeography.pdf#page=23</refid>
        <name type="book">Baca, Murtha et. al. Cataloging Cultural Objects: A Guide to Describing Cultural Works and Their Images. Chicago: American Library Association, 2006, 205.</name>
    </source>
</sourceSet>
        <stylePeriodSet>
    <display/>
    <notes/>
    <stylePeriod pref="false" refid="300021279" source="getty" type="styleperiods" vocab="aat">Second Empire</stylePeriod>
</stylePeriodSet>
        <subjectSet>
    <display/>
    <notes/>
    <subject dataDate="2015-04-22-14-44-39" pref="false" refid="300001892" vocab="aat">
        <term type="otherTopic">trusses</term>
    </subject>
    <subject pref="false" refid="300055499" vocab="aat">
        <term type="conceptTopic">government</term>
    </subject>
    <subject dataDate="2015-04-22-14-41-10" pref="false" refid="300005969" vocab="aat">
        <term type="otherTopic">courthouses</term>
    </subject>
    <subject dataDate="2016-03-24-09-20-14" pref="false" refid="300263552" vocab="aat">
        <term type="descriptiveTopic">architecture</term>
    </subject>
</subjectSet>
        <techniqueSet>
    <display/>
    <notes/>
    <technique pref="false" refid="300386948" source="getty" type="techniques" vocab="aat">stonemasonry</technique>
</techniqueSet>
        <textrefSet>
    <display/>
    <notes/>
    <textref dataDate="2016-03-24-09-10-25" pref="false">
        <name type="electronic">CONA</name>
        <refid type="URI">http://www.getty.edu/cona/CONAFullSubject.aspx?subid=700000168</refid>
    </textref>
</textrefSet>
        <titleSet>
    <display/>
    <notes/>
    <title pref="false" type="popular">Bartholomew County Courthouse</title>
    <title pref="true" type="popular">Columbus Courthouse</title>
</titleSet>
        <vra:relationSet xmlns:vra="http://www.vraweb.org/vracore4.htm">
            <vra:relation type="imageIs" relids="i_e139cc13-fecb-4adc-9a64-7067518a2442" source="Tamboti" pref="true">general view</vra:relation>
            <vra:relation type="imageIs" relids="i_bfd2e88b-6aff-4143-8fb4-9e2429f25744" source="Tamboti" pref="false">general view</vra:relation>
        </vra:relationSet>
        <worktypeSet>
    <display/>
    <notes/>
    <worktype pref="false" refid="300005969" source="getty" type="worktypes" vocab="aat">courthouses</worktype>
            <worktype pref="false" refid="300263552" source="getty" type="worktypes" vocab="aat">architecture</worktype>
</worktypeSet>
    </work>
</vra>